N178QS: Lisboa Arrival good evening,
N178QS, FL250, inbound to LAZET,
Information K
Time: 18:50 UTC on December 30, 2025
Arrival ATIS:
LPPT ARR ATIS K
1830Z EXP ILS APCH RWY IN USE 02
TRL 50 AFTER LDG VACATE VIA H" 4
BIRD ACTIVITY WND TDZ 030 DEG 4
KT VIS 10KM CLD FEW 1200 FT
TEMP 9 DP 8 QNH 1020 ACK ARR
INFO K
Lisboa Approach: N178QS, Lisboa
Arrival boa tarde, identified. Descend
FL80. Proceed direct RULOX, cleared
LAZET arrival, expect ILS runway 02.
Information K is now current, QNH 1020
Departure ATIS:
LPPT DEP ATIS S
1314Z RWY IN USE 02 TRL 50 FIRST
CONTACT ON DELIVERY FREQ
118.955 WND MID 030 DEG 4 KT VRB
BTN 010 AND 090 DEG END 060 DEG
4 KT VRB BTN 320 AND 110 DEG VIS
MID 2700M END 400M RVR MID ABV
2000M END 500M PRFG CLD SCT
200 FT. SCT 400 FT TEMP 8 DP 8
QNH 1021 ACK DEP INFO S
N178QS: Descend FL80, QNH 1020,
direct RULOX, cleared LAZET arrival,
expect ILS runway 02, N178QS
TAP438T: Lisbon Delivery, boa tarde,
TAP438T, stand 124, information S,
ready to copy
Lisboa Delivery: TAP438T, boa tarde,
Lisboa Delivery, information S is
current, QNH 1020. Runway 02 in use.
Cleared to Paris Orly as filed. Expect
departure via IXIDA SID. Squawk 4314.
Initial climb to 4000 feet.
TAP438T: QNH 1020. Cleared to Paris
Orly as filed. Expect departure via
IXIDA SID. Squawk 4314. Initial climb to
4000 feet, TAP438T
Lisboa Delivery: TAP438T, readback
correct, when ready contact Lisboa
Ground on 121.755, boa viagem
TAP438T: Contact Lisboa Ground on
121.755, obrigado, TAP438T
TAP438T: Lisbon Ground, boa tarde,
TAP438T, stand 124, request pushback
and startup
Lisboa Ground: TAP438T, boa tarde,
identified, pushback and startup
approved, facing north. Expect taxi via
A3, G, U1, N2 to runway 02.
TAP438T: Pushback and startup
approved, facing north. Expect taxi via
A3, G, U1, N2 to runway 02, obrigado,
TAP438T
EZS54LR: Lisbon Delivery, good
afternoon, EZS54LR, stand 115,
information S, ready to copy
Lisboa Delivery: EZS54LR, boa tarde,
Lisboa Delivery, information S is
current, QNH 1020. Runway 02 in use.
Cleared to Geneva as filed. Expect
departure via IXIDA SID. Squawk 4309.
Initial climb to 4000 feet.
EZS54LR: QNH 1020. Cleared to
Geneva as filed. Expect departure via
IXIDA SID. Squawk 4309. Initial climb
to 4000 feet, EZS54LR
Lisboa Delivery: EZS54LR, readback
correct, when ready contact Lisboa
Ground on 121.755, boa viagem
EZS54LR: Contact Lisboa Ground on
121.755, obrigado, EZS54LR
EZS54LR: Lisbon Ground, boa tarde,
EZS54LR, stand 115, request pushback
and startup
Lisboa Ground: EZS54LR, boa tarde,
identified, pushback and startup
approved, facing south. Expect taxi via
A2, M to runway 02.
EZS54LR: Pushback and startup
approved, facing south. Expect taxi via
A2, M to runway 02, obrigado,
EZS54LR
TAP438T: Lisbon Ground, TAP438T,
ready to taxi
Lisboa Ground: TAP438T, taxi to
runway 02 via A3, G, U1, N2, hold short
runway 02. Monitor tower on 118.105
TAP438T: Taxi to runway 02 via A3, G,
U1, N2, hold short runway 02. Monitor
tower on 118.105, TAP438T
EZS54LR: Lisbon Ground, EZS54LR,
ready to taxi
Lisboa Ground: EZS54LR, taxi to
runway 02 via A2, M, hold short runway
02. Monitor tower on 118.105
EZS54LR: Taxi to runway 02 via A2,
M, hold short runway 02. Monitor tower
on 118.105, EZS54LR
Lisboa Ground: handoff to tower for
TAP438T
TAP438T: Lisbon Tower, boa tarde,
TAP438T, ready for departure runway
Lisboa Tower: TAP438T, boa tarde,
wind 030 degrees, 4 knots, runway 02
cleared for takeoff. Initial climb to
4000 feet, after departure contact
Lisboa Departure on 119.105
TAP438T: Runway 02 cleared for
takeoff. Initial climb to 4000 feet,
after departure contact Lisboa
Departure on 119.105, obrigado,
TAP438T
Lisboa Ground: handoff to tower for
EZS54LR
EZS54LR: Lisbon Tower, good
afternoon, EZS54LR, ready for
departure runway 02
Lisboa Tower: EZS54LR, boa tarde,
wind 030 degrees, 4 knots, line up and
wait behind TAP Airbus runway 02
EZS54LR: Line up and wait behind TAP
Airbus runway 02, EZS54LR
Lisboa Tower: EZS54LR, runway 02
cleared for takeoff. Initial climb to
4000 feet, after departure contact
Lisboa Departure on 119.105
EZS54LR: Runway 02 cleared for
takeoff. Initial climb to 4000 feet,
after departure contact Lisboa
Departure on 119.105, thank you,
EZS54LR
TAP438T: Lisbon Departure, boa tarde,
TAP438T, passing 2,300 feet climbing
4,000 feet, on IXIDA departure
340 was the planned flight level of
TP440 (not TP438 because that one
was operated with an A332) on the 30th
of december 2025, this information
wasn't in the provided simulation file
Lisboa Approach: TAP438T, boa tarde,
identified. Climb via SID to FL340,
have a safe flight
TAP438T: Climb via SID to FL340,
obrigado TAP438T
Lisboa Approach: N178QS, proceed
direct MAZUK
N178QS: Direct MAZUK, N178QS
EZS54LR: Lisbon Departure, good
evening, EZS54LR, passing 1,500 feet
climbing 4,000 feet, on IXIDA departure
I forgot to assume it in the simulation,
but this doesn't affect anything
380 was the planned flight level of
U21466 (not U21462 due to timing not
lining up with the chosen ATIS, maybe the
day of the simulation it was delayed) on
the 30th of december 2025, this
information wasn't in the provided
simulation file
Lisboa Approach: EZS54LR, boa tarde,
identified. Climb via SID to FL380,
have a safe flight
EZS54LR: Climb via SID to FL380,
thank you EZS54LR
DLH97V: Lisboa Arrival good evening,
DLH97V, FL350, inbound to INBOM,
Information K
We override the simulation to put
DLH97V still at FL350 like their
flight plan says instead of at FL137
descending because it feels like too soon
and weird for the en-route to already
have cleared the descent when the TMA
extends so far north, unlike the western
TMA border which is much closer to the
airport
Lisboa Approach: DLH97V, Lisboa
Arrival boa tarde, identified. For
sequencing, proceed direct XAMAX,
cleared XAMAX arrival. When ready
descend FL80, expect ILS runway 02.
QNH 1020.
I forgot to assume it in the simulation,
that's why XAMAX becomes orange and
then resets to INBOM, then I assume
them and do it again
DLH97V: Direct XAMAX, cleared
XAMAX arrival, when ready descend
FL80, expect ILS runway 02, QNH
1020, DLH97V
Lisboa Approach: N178QS, proceed
direct PESEX, descend 4000 feet, QNH
N178QS: Direct PESEX, descend 4000
feet, QNH 1020, N178QS
In the simulation I assume EZS54LR but
in the communication this actually
already happened
TAP43RY: Lisboa Arrival boa tarde,
TAP43RY, FL390, inbound to INBOM,
Information K
We override the simulation to put
TAP43RY still at FL390 like their
flight plan says instead of at FL145
descending because it feels like too soon
and weird for the en-route to already
have cleared the descent when the TMA
extends so far north, unlike the western
TMA border which is much closer to the
airport
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, Lisboa
Arrival boa tarde, identified. When
ready descend FL80. Cleared INBOM
arrival, expect ILS runway 02.
Information K is now current, QNH 1020
TAP43RY: When ready descend FL80,
cleared INBOM arrival, expect ILS
runway 02, QNH 1020, TAP43RY
In the simulation I clear Lufthansa and
TAP43RY to FL80 only now, this is
because, since I told them to descend
when ready, we assume they decided this
is their calculated top of descent. This
was the only way to make the simulation
understand this. The simulation will now
make them descend at 1600 fpm but in
reality they would use a managed descent
and be at FL80 at MAZUK
In the simulation you see TAP43RY
reaching INBOM and continuing on
heading 219. This is wrong. In reality, we
cleared them for the INBOM arrival so
they would turn towards the next
waypoint after INBOM which is PT808
Lisboa Approach: DLH97V, proceed
direct NATID
DLH97V: Direct NATID, DLH97V
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, proceed
direct ODLIX
TAP43RY: Direct ODLIX, TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: N178QS, cleared ILS
approach runway 02
N178QS: Cleared ILS approach runway
02, N178QS
Lisboa Approach: N178QS, contact
Lisboa Tower 118.105, tchau
N178QS: 118.105, goodbye, N178QS
N178QS: Lisbon Tower, good evening,
N178QS, on final for runway 02
Lisboa Tower: N178QS, boa tarde,
identified, wind 030 degrees, 4 knots,
runway 02 cleared to land. Vacate via
H4 if able. Contact ground on 118.105
after arrival
N178QS: Runway 02 cleared to land,
vacate via H4 if able. Contact ground on
118.105 after arrival, thanks, N178QS
N178QS: Lisbon Ground, good evening,
N178QS, vacated runway 02 on H4,
request taxi to stand 705
Lisboa Ground: N178QS, boa tarde,
identified, taxi to stand 705 via U4,
A5, W1, D
N178QS: Taxi to stand 705 via U4, A5,
W1, D, thanks, N178QS
Lisboa Approach: TAP438T, contact
Lisboa Control 132.305, boa viagem
TAP is being handed off to the North
Lower Sector of the Lisboa ACC since
they are at FL340 and that sector does
SFC to FL345
TAP438T: 132.305, obrigado,
TAP438T
Easyjet is being handed off to the
North Upper Sector of the Lisboa ACC
since they are at FL380 and that
sector does FL365 to UNL
Lisboa Approach: EZS54LR, contact
Lisboa Control 134.855, boa viagem
EZS54LR: 134.855, obrigado,
EZS54LR
In the simulation we make sure the plane
is going to MAZUK now that it is almost
at NATID, but this doesn't require
communication since in reality the pilots
would just follow the arrival as cleared
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, descend
4000 feet, QNH 1020
TAP43RY: Descend 4000 feet, QNH
1020, TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, proceed
direct PESEX
TAP43RY: Direct PESEX, TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, cleared
ILS approach runway 02
TAP43RY: Cleared ILS approach runway
02, TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: DLH97V, proceed
direct PESEX, descend 4000 feet, QNH
DLH97V: Direct PESEX, descend 4000
feet, QNH 1020, DLH97V
Lisboa Approach: TAP43RY, contact
Lisboa Tower 118.105, tchau
TAP43RY: 118.105, tchau, TAP43RY
TAP43RY: Lisbon Tower, boa tarde,
TAP43RY, on final for runway 02
Lisboa Tower: TAP43RY, boa tarde,
identified, wind 030 degrees, 4 knots,
runway 02 cleared to land. Vacate via
H4 if able. Contact ground on 118.105
after arrival
TAP43RY: Runway 02 cleared to land,
vacate via H4 if able. Contact ground on
118.105 after arrival, obrigado,
TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: DLH97V, cleared ILS
approach runway 02
DLH97V: Cleared ILS approach runway
02, DLH97V
TAP43RY: Lisbon Ground, boa tarde,
TAP43RY, vacated runway 02 on H4,
request taxi to stand 124
Lisboa Ground: TAP43RY, boa tarde,
identified, taxi to stand 124 via U4, A
TAP43RY: Taxi to stand 124 via U4, A,
obrigado, TAP43RY
Lisboa Approach: DLH97V, contact
Lisboa Tower 118.105, tchau
DLH97V: 118.105, goodbye, DLH97V
DLH97V: Lisbon Tower, good evening,
DLH97V, on final for runway 02
Lisboa Tower: DLH97V, good evening,
identified, wind 030 degrees, 4 knots,
runway 02 cleared to land. Vacate via
H4 if able. Contact ground on 118.105
after arrival
DLH97V: Runway 02 cleared to land,
vacate via H4 if able. Contact ground on
118.105 after arrival, thanks, DLH97V
DLH97V: Lisbon Ground, good evening,
DLH97V, vacated runway 02 on H4,
request taxi to stand 115
Lisboa Ground: DLH97V, good evening,
identified, taxi to stand 115 via U4, A
DLH97V: Taxi to stand 115 via U4, A,
thanks, DLH97V